Today's דף daf is פ"ח, Peh Chet, we're almost done with the
פרק, perek, we begin at the bottom of פ"ז עמוד ב' Peh
Zayin Amud Bet and we were talking about
blood getting mixed up with water and other liquids and when is
it still considered blood. And the last issue had been about whether
it's considered blood for הכשר זרעים hechsher zera'im when liquids come in
contact with foodstuff, they make it susceptible for becoming טמא. tamei. So
what would be the status if it was some type of blood
mixed with rain water? Okay, now we are continuing a few more
comments about the nature of blood or blood mixtures. Let's take a
look.
Okay, רבי אסי, Rabbi Assi, the line starts with the word אסי,
Assi, it is eight lines from the bottom. רבי אסי מנהרויל Rabbi
Assi mi-Naharville אומר, omer, רבי אסי Rabbi Assi from נהרויל Naharville says,
בצילותא דדמא. b'tzilusah d'dama. Now,
when we had that earlier statement that as long as something still
looks red it is מכשיר זרעים, machshir zera'im, the גמרא Gemara said,
well, who cares? If it's mixed with water, water does it anyway.
So what's the חידוש? chiddush? So it had the example of mixed
with rain water. He says, no, we're talking about the clear part
of the blood which, as רש"י Rashi says, is if you let
blood sit and then you know, obviously the more I guess
non-liquid matter, what do you call non-liquid, the solid matter,
collects towards the middle and at the edges it's more clearer and
there's more just of the water, the water that's a natural part
of the blood. So even that, even though it looks even though
it's the clear liquid of the blood, it still is מכשיר זרעים,
machshir zera'im, it still is considered blood. רבי ירמיה מדיפתי Rabbi Yirmiyah
mi-Difti אמר, amar, רבי ירמיה Rabbi Yirmiyah from דיפתי Difti says, אין
בו כרת. ein bo kares. Now,
it's a question whether this what this is going on. Is this
is going on blood mixed with water, you know, and the mixtures
we talked about before, or is this going on the immediate previous
line which is the water of the blood?
רש"י Rashi a little ambiguous. תוספות Tosafot says that it's going on
both, that you get כרת kares even for this water of the
blood because originally that was all blood, it just now has a
little bit separated into its component parts. But then there's an interesting
qualification. והוא דאיכא כזית, v'hu d'ika k'zayis, only if there is a
כזית kezayis there. Now of course you need a כזית kezayis normally
of blood to get כרת, kares, so what's the חידוש? chiddush? The
חידוש chiddush seems to be there's only a כזית kezayis of real
blood there. Now again, if it's blood mixed with water and say
if you drink this blood that was mixed with water, you're transgressing
the biblical prohibition of drinking blood and you get כרת, kares, but
of course there has to be an actual כזית kezayis of the
real prohibited substance, not of the mixture, right? If you had חזיר
chazir mixed with water or let's say חזיר chazir and vegetables, you
wouldn't transgress for a כזית kezayis of the stew, you'd only transgress
if there was an actual כזית kezayis of חזיר chazir of the
stew that you ingested. So here too if it's blood mixed with
water, you only transgress if you actually sure you eat the mixture,
you can transgress, but only if you actually eat a כזית kezayis
of the blood itself. That's sort of very straightforward. If it's referring
even to the water of the blood, not a mixture, but the
water that is sort of you know that's part of the blood
itself, then it's then it's like it's not only is it a
big חידוש chiddush but it almost completely neutralizes the past statement. It
says that if you eat this, let's say you had blood, you
put it on the table or whatever and you know some of
it the solid collected in the middle, the liquid the clearer liquid
remained at the end and now you consumed it. So since even
though there's a כזית kezayis total, since only the red matter was
less than a כזית, kezayis, therefore you don't transgress. So if that's
true, then you're basically saying that the water of the blood when
it separates is not blood. It seems to be though maybe it's
saying a middle position. It's not enough blood to get כרת, kares,
but it's enough related to the blood that it can be מכשיר
זרעים, machshir zera'im, that it can make the food susceptible. So then
it really is a חידוש, chiddush, but then it's saying in a
very you know a very unusual middle position.
What if you could reconstitute blood, right, like with orange juice?
If it lost its status, would it regain it? That's like another
חוזר וניעור chozer v'neia type of a question. So you know, that's
an excellent question. I will tell you that somebody asked,
I forget which, I think the ציץ אליעזר, Tzitz Eliezer, can you
make קידוש kiddush on reconstituted grape juice? So he says before you
ask if you can קידוש kiddush on reconstituted grape juice, ask me
if you can say בורא פרי הגפן Borei Pri HaGafen on reconstituted
grape juice.
And even if it's not reconstituted, there's a question about that, but
we'll bracket that for now too. Anyway, so yeah, that is an
interesting question. If you reconstitute things, do they retain their status? You
know, and how much
did it keep its status when it was de-reconstituted or whatever, the
more it can obviously keep its status if it's reconstituted. But anyway,
here let's just finish this. Here it might be saying this interesting
middle status of the water element of the blood.
תנא, tana, okay, so במתניתא תנא, b'masnisa tana, in a ברייתא braita
we taught, מטמאים באהל, mitamin b'ohel, it causes טומאה tumah in an
אהל. ohel. Again, does this mean a blood water mixture, or does
this mean the water component of the blood? And then again we
have another qualifier, והוא דאיכא רביעית, v'hu d'ika revieis, only if there's
a רביעית. revieis. We know you need a רביעית revieis of blood
to cause טומאת אהל. tumas ohel. So again, if it's blood mixed
with water, it's obvious. And it makes sense, you know, you have
blood mixed with water, you put it in, of a blood of
a dead... of a corpse, of a human corpse, and it's in
a room, it causes טומאה tumah in the room, but only if
there's a real... a רביעית revit of the blood, not of the
mixture, but of the blood itself. So even if it's mixed with
something else, as long as you have a full רביעית revit of
the blood itself. If it's talking again about the liquid of the
blood, the water component of the blood, then it really becomes a
moot statement, because the water component doesn't cause... cause טומאה, tumah, only...
then what it's saying is only the red component causes טומאה. tumah.
So again, if you read the גמרא Gemara that way, what it's
really saying is the water component might be enough of a liquid
and enough related to blood to do הכשר זרעים, hechsher z'rayim, but
it's not enough to transgress eating blood or to cause טומאה tumah
in אוהל. ohel. For that you need the actual solid component, the
red aspect component of the blood, and not just the clear liquid
that's separated off. You had a question?
Is there to be dried blood maybe?
Yes, dried blood could also cause... this would apply to dried blood
as well, that's true.
But it's still got to be some blood or whatever it is.
What? Yeah, that would also be more likely to be caked on
blood.
That could be, but then the difference still between what's the blood
and the sort of if it dried and some liquid separated, here
we're saying that that liquid is not enough to get כרת karet
or to cause טומאה tumah in אוהל. ohel.
This liquid is the blood plasma or something?
I guess it is, yeah, plasma...
probably plasma. Okay.
תנן התם. Tnan hatam. So we taught over there in a... now
of course, if you look at the side it says... on the
left-hand side it says תוספתא, Tosefta, and on the right-hand side it
quotes the ר"ש, Rash, not the ר"א, Rosh, the ר"ש, Rash, רבי
שמשון, Rabbi Shimshon, one of the בעלי התוספות, Ba'alei haTosafot, who writes
a commentary on משניות, Mishnayot, who says all of the manuscripts say
תנן, Tnan, we taught in a משנה, Mishnah, but it's in no
משנה. Mishnah. It's only in a תוספתא. Tosefta. Okay. So anyway... What?
תוספות Tosafot says the גמרא Gemara does sometimes do that, either by
mistake or by being not precise. Yes.
From observation it seems that the opposite is the case when the
blood evaporates or dries. The other... you ever have, you know...
Oh, the liquid collects in the middle and the... That's actually true.
...and the red stuff
is exposed to the air. You know, that's actually a good point.
I was describing it the way the ר"ש Rash described it, but
actually, because also, you know, we teach סימנים simanim here in the
ישיבה Yeshiva and, that's also something that's...
That's when it's absorbed into a cloth.
Oh, you think it has to do with the cloth as well?
That's how we level-explain it when we do the מראות, marot, the...
you look at them on the edges because that's where the stuff...
that's because of the way it absorbs into the cloth.
Oh, into cloth? So maybe it depends on the surface, I don't
know. If we... alright, we'll have to... we'll have either look it
up on Wikipedia or get some scientists in here. Get Charlie back
in here. תנן התם. Tnan hatam. Okay. כל
משקה מת טהורים חוץ מדמו. Kol mashke meit tehorim chutz midamo. So
we taught in the משנה, Mishnah, but it really isn't a משנה.
Mishnah. All liquids of a corpse are טהור, tahor, they're not considered
like the corpse itself, except for the blood. The blood of the
corpse, as we just said, causes טומאה tumah and even causes טומאה
tumah in a... in a tent, meaning under a roof, everything under
the roof.
וכל מראי אדמומית שבו מטמאין באוהל. V'chol marei admumit shebo metam'in b'ohel.
And all reddish sort of appearances causes טומאה tumah in the tent,
which again, that does sound similar to the previous point, which means
it could mean again a mixture of blood with other things as
long as it still looks red, which is what we said earlier,
or it could mean, and this is what it sounds, even if
the blood is not... doesn't... isn't like deep red. Even if it's
just as a little reddish, you know, maybe and it's a more
liquidy part of blood, that still is considered to be blood. ומשקי
המת טהורין. Umashkei hameit tehorin. But any other liquids of the corpse
are טהור, tahor, which seems to be... that whole thing seemed a
little repetitive, but anyway that's the point. Blood and anything that is...
that you know even if it doesn't have a deep red appearance
is טמא tamei and causes טומאה tumah even under... even in... even
under a roof, but all other liquids are not a problem and
don't have the טומאה tumah of a corpse. So the גמרא Gemara
says רמינהו, raminihu, I'll ask him on that to say that the
other liquids do not have the טומאה tumah of a corpse. משקה
טבול יום. Mashkeh tvul yom. We say that the liquids coming from
a טבול יום. tvul yom. א טבול יום tvul yom is a
person that has gone to the מקוה, mikvah, טובל, tovel, on that
day, and will become טהור tahor that night after sunset. And his
status is equivalent to that of a שני. sheni. So if he
touches תרומה terumah he makes it טמא, tamei, he can't eat תרומה,
terumah, but other than... but that's his status. Now, let's say liquids
emerge from his body like spit or urine or blood or tears.
What is the status of those liquids? So this... so this... so
this משנה Mishnah teaches כמשקין שנוגע בהן, k'mashkin shenogea bahen, it's like
he touched them. Now, if a שני sheni touches liquids, what's the
status? So a normal שני sheni who touches liquids, for example, a
rabbinic institution is that your hands are considered שני, sheni, second derivative
טומאה, tumah, and the... when they... when they get... get wet they
actually tran...
the water actually goes up to becoming a ראשון. rishon. It's a
unique quality of water, שני sheni touching a water, that the water
goes up to become a ראשון, rishon, which by the way, is
why you have to dry your hands after you do נטילת ידיים.
netilat yadayim. Because why did we do נטילת ידיים netilat yadayim all
together? Because they would do... wash their hands when כהנים Kohanim before
they would eat תרומה. terumah. Because if their hands are a שני,
sheni, the תרומה terumah would become invalid. שני sheni can make תרומה
terumah invalid. So we wash our hands, but washing your hands isn't
enough. That was the way normally biblically you cannot... To do טהרה
Taharah unless your whole body goes into the מקוה. Mikvah. Also, not
only part of your body could be טמא, Tamei, but once the
Rabbis said rabbinically your hands could be טמא, Tamei, they also allowed
for a way to purify just your hands and wash them. But
if there's liquid on them, then the liquid actually goes up to
becoming a ראשון, Rishon, so actually you have to you have to
dry your hands. Now it's not so
easy
like that because I should say and I'm getting a little digressing
because because if that were true, then why would it why would
it work all together? Why not as soon as you have liquid
on your hand, you're touching it and your hands become טמא Tamei
again? Anyway, but for example, if you know another just simple example
about this is why we do נטילת ידיים Netilat Yadayim before we
dip כרפס Karpas on the סדר Seder night is because since the
כרפס Karpas has a liquid on it, so if your hands touch
the liquid, they make the liquid a ראשון Rishon and everything starts
going up levels. So maybe we don't have to do that generally,
that's debated, but anyway, that's the general principle is that normally if
a שני Sheni touches something liquid, it goes up to being a
ראשון. Rishon. However, the exception to this is a טבול יום. Tevul
Yom. A טבול יום Tevul Yom is on his way out of
becoming טמא, Tamei, that night he'll be טהור. Tahor. There they did
not have that that restriction that
and therefore if he touches something, it will not become טמא. Tamei.
So the ruling of this is liquid. If liquids come out of
a טבול יום, Tevul Yom, urine, spit, whatever, tears, blood, they are
like he touched it, which means they're nothing. They are not טמא
Tamei because he's a טבול יום. Tevul Yom. And thus we read
the top line, ואלו ואלו אין מטמאין, V'eilu v'eilu ein metamin, they
do not cause טומאה. Tumah. However, ושאר כל הטמאים, U'sh'ar kol hatemei'im,
all other impure people, בין קלים בין חמורים, Bein kalim bein chamurim,
whether they are a high level of impurity or a low level
of impurity, right? A low level would be let's say they're a
ראשון, Rishon, they touched a שרץ. Sheretz. A high level of impurity
would be let's say they're an אב, Av, they touched a dead
body. Whether they're a high or a low level of impurity,
משקין היוצא מהן כמשקה שנוגע בהן, Mashkin hayotzei meihen k'mashkeh shenogea bahen,
liquids that come from them is like they touched the liquid. So
what happens if you're an if you're an אב Av or a
ראשון Rishon or even a שני Sheni that touched liquid? You make
it into a ראשון. Rishon. ואלו ואלו תחילה. V'eilu v'eilu techilah. So
whatever you are, right, the highest thing you could be would be
an אב הטומאה. Av HaTumah. So an אב הטומאה Av HaTumah who
touches a liquid, it goes down one level is a ראשון. Rishon.
But because of the special qualities of liquids, even if you're a
ראשון Rishon or שני Sheni and you touch a liquid, it goes
up to being a ראשון. Rishon. So anybody other than the טבול
יום, Tevul Yom, liquids that emerge from that person are like you
touched the liquids and therefore the liquid is a ראשון. Rishon. חוץ,
Chutz, one minute, מן המשקה שהוא אב הטומאה. Min hamashkeh shehu av
hatumah. The only exception is sometimes liquids themselves are an אב הטומאה.
Av HaTumah. Which liquids are the אבות הטומאה? Avot HaTumah? Liquids of
people who are טמא Tamei because of the very types of of
liquids that emerge from their body themselves. So a נידה, Niddah, a
זבה, Zavah, a זב, Zav, these types of people, right, that are
טמא Tamei exactly because of certain things that have emerged from their
body themselves, their liquids are טמא. Tamei. Not all their liquids, but
basically their spit, their blood, and their urine. So their spit and
their blood and their urine themselves is an אב הטומאה. Av HaTumah.
So those are the one exceptions of certain people whose certain bodily
fluids, fluids is probably the better word than liquid, whose certain bodily
fluids are an אב. Av. But other than those people and those
with those fluids, any other fluid that emerges from a טמא Tamei
person's body is like he touched it and it's a ראשון. Rishon.
Mordechai, you had a question?
Always a clarification. Yes. We're excluding קרי Keri from that last list?
I was going to ask you about this recently.
About קרי, Keri, right,
the קרי Keri of a בעל קרי, Ba'al Keri, that's a good
point, I should have mentioned that. The קרי Keri of a בעל
there actually is a מחלוקת if the קרי Keri of a בעל
קרי Ba'al Keri is an אב Av or a wait, am I
getting that wrong? No, there's a question about the status of there's
a whole question whether a בעל קרי Ba'al Keri is a רואה
ro'eh or נוגע. nogea. But anyway, yes, yes, I have to double
check, but yes, the בעל קרי Ba'al Keri would be included, I
mean the קרי Keri of a בעל קרי. Ba'al Keri.
Now there's a clarification point. When you said that rabbinically...
oh,
one minute, one minute, what did I so what did I say
when I said the liquids? Spit, urine, and semen. I think I
said I think I said blood. I so I misspoke. I'm sorry.
So I misspoke. So the liquids of yes, so the liquids I
so I misspoke. So thank you. Yes, so the liquids of these
people whose liquids whose fluids are אב, Av, like the זב Zav
and the זבה Zavah and the נידה Niddah or whatever, is the
semen, the the urine, and what did I say? Semen, urine, and
spit. The basic way the Rabbis say it is it's types of
things that collect in the body before they come out. But not
the blood? So not the blood. Not the blood. So semen, spit,
and urine because all of those collect first in the body in
some type of place and before they emerge. What?
And you mentioned tears before.
Tears would not. Tears and blood would not for it would be
a ראשון, Rishon, but not an אב. Av. The Torah speaks about
וכי ירוק. V'chi yarok. וכי ירוק הזב על הטהור, V'chi yarok hazav
al hatahor, right, this speaks about spitting. So from spit, the גמרא
Gemara learns things that are like spitting that collect in the body
before coming out, which they say also includes
semen and urine, but not blood and not tears.
Okay, and then the other funny clarification. When you say that hands
are מדרבנן m'derabbanan
שני Sheni that cause ראשון, Rishon, is that when you are yourself
a ראשון, Rishon, the rest of your body, or when the rest
of your body is?
No, even if the rest of your body is nothing. Because we
don't know where your hands have gotten to. That was one I
wanted to clarify. Yeah. Why not tears?
Do tears collect in tear ducts?
I mean, people can, it's not like... no, I mean, I know
there are tear ducts, but if you cry it will, to spit
you got to collect your you've got to collect your spit, right?
No, there is a difference, isn't there? The way the way urine
and spit and semen you have to collect and sweat...
same thing as sweat... same thing as tears?
Wikipedia question. Anyway, what's sweat? Yeah, same as tears. It's not. Okay,
so anyway, moving on. So now the גמרא Gemara says, ah, so
what's our question? So it says all other liquids are like you
touched them. So therefore, and there's some that are even worse, but
at least they're like you touched them. So that should mean that
a liquid that emerges from a corpse, even if it's not blood,
right, so the blood is only by the corpse, other things it's
not the blood. In the liquid... but it said that anything that's
not blood that comes from a corpse is טהור. tahor. Here we're
saying that at least it's going to be a ראשון. rishon. So
the גמרא Gemara
says: מאי קלין ומאי חמורין? Mai kalin u-mai hamurin? What do you
mean the more stringent and the more weighty
טמא? tamei? So מאי לאו, mai lav, do we not mean קלין?
kalin? People that are less that are not as that are not
as weighty, שרץ? sheretz? If you touch their bug, a rodent, a
dead rodent, and you're a ראשון. rishon.
וזב, v'zav, and a זב? zav? Now why is a זב, zav,
right, because he's an אב, av, but there's something even higher than
an אב, av, there's a corpse itself, which is the אבי אבות,
avi avot, the grandaddy of טומאה. tumah. So וחמורין, ve-hamurin, the weighty
is מת, met, is a corpse? So you see even liquids that
emerge from a מת, met, it says are טמא, tamei, right, it's,
and you're saying that they were טהור. tahor. It says: לא, קלין
שרץ, Lo, kalin sheretz, the light ones are somebody who touched a
rodent, a dead rodent, which makes him a ראשון. rishon. וחמורין, Ve-hamurin,
the more heavy ones are זב, zav, a person with a man
with with an unnatural flow, which makes him an אב. av. So
and those liquids that emerge from them, even when they're not like
the spit and the urine, those liquids are like they touched them
and they're ראשון. rishon. But by a מת met the liquids are
טהור, tahor, which is quite ironic. A מת met which is the
most weighty of טומאות, tumot, why should the liquids that emerge be
טהור? tahor? So the גמרא Gemara says: מאי שנא זב דגזרו ביה
רבנן ומאי שנא מת דלא גזרו ביה רבנן? Mai shena zav de-gazru
bei rabbanan u-mai shena met de-lo gazru bei rabbanan? What's the difference
by a זב zav where these liquids the Rabbis made a גזירה,
gezeirah, we'll talk in a minute why we're assuming it's rabbinic, and
by the corpse the liquids that come out that's not the blood,
there is no גזירה? gezeirah? So it's it's very ironic. So it
says: זב דלא בדילי אינשי מיניה גזרו ביה רבנן. zav de-lo badili
inshi minei gazru bei rabbanan. A זב, zav, people don't separate from
a זב. zav. First of all, they don't find it repulsive. And
number two is, as רש"י Rashi says, nobody knows who's a זב.
zav. Who knows who's a זב, zav, who's a זב, who's a
נדה? niddah? Since you don't know, so therefore you're more likely to
touch that person and become טמא. tamei. So since you're more likely
to touch that person and become טמא, tamei, we had to almost
safeguard it and warn you stay away even from their if you're
trying to keep טהור, tahor, not if you're just not worrying about
טומאה וטהרה, tumah ve-taharah, but if you're trying to be טהור, tahor,
you have to stay away even from their liquids. And that helps
sort of keep people on guard. Because otherwise people are just very
would be careless. מת דבדילי אינשי מיניה. Met de-badili inshi minei. A
corpse, which people in general try to avoid it, unless of course
you have to deal with like a funeral which, anyway, sadly we've
had a few in this שול shul recently. But anyway, number one,
people in general avoid it. And as רש"י Rashi also says, people
know what a corpse is. It's not like they don't know. So
therefore they naturally keep their distance if they're trying to be טהור.
tahor. So לא גזרו ביה רבנן, lo gazru bei rabbanan, we didn't
have to extend it by also adding to the liquids. Now, תוספות
Tosafot asks a question. So we basically have said what?
Certain sources of טומאה, tumah, their liquids are טמא, tamei, like themselves.
A corpse, the blood is, because that's like the life force, that
makes sense. By a זב, זבה, zavah, ונדה, ve-niddah, certain liquids that
are that the תורה Torah speaks about spitting, but the but חז"ל
Chazal extend understand that that's not limited to spitting and includes even
spit what we've said, spit, urine, and semen. Those are actually אבות
הטומאה avot ha-tumah themselves. But why are we saying that all other
liquids is rabbinic? I mean when a liquid comes out of a
body, it's touching the body. Shouldn't that be biblical? So okay, so
let's say tears come out of a מת, met, or whatever. Do
tears emerge after death? Whatever. Anyway, some type of a liquid is
coming out after death. It's touching the skin, right? If it's touching
the skin, so biblically it should be טמא. tamei. It should be,
it touches a corpse, it should be an אב av or should
be a ראשון, rishon, whatever it should be. So anyway, what's the
answer? So תוספות Tosafot gives two answers. One, תוספות Tosafot says we're
talking about a very hypothetical case, which is that you attach some
type of a siphon to the to the dead body and the
liquid came away from the dead body without ever touching the skin.
Okay? Or I guess you could imagine a case where maybe it
was the body was suspended and something was dripping through some type
of a some type of a grate without actually having come out
of the body, but it didn't touch the surface skin. That's one
case, very unusual.
What same thing by נדה?
Similar. Anyway, the other answer תוספות Tosafot says is that no, maybe
that... these types of liquids like tears and urine and so on
are not generally considered liquids. So therefore, right, a מת Meis can
only be מטמא Metamei something for example, you know, a dead body
can't be מטמא Metamei a rock, it can only be basically what
can טומאה Tumah things be מטמא? Metamei? People, food, and vessels. So
if these things that are emerging are not considered biblically liquids, so
even though they're touching the body, they would not become טמא Tamei
and therefore would only be... Why wouldn't it be biblical liquid? Because
they're not in a normal... right?
No, hello? Why shouldn't it be מטמא, Metamei,
isn't it?
Well, yeah, because במאהל. B'Ohel. A dead body in an אהל.
Ohel. Yeah, well that's what I'm saying. Is it מטמא Metamei dirt?
Is it מטמא Metamei rock?
No, no, but why wouldn't it be considered liquid?
So there's only seven things that are formally recognized as liquids and
tears are not one of them, you know, urine is not one
of them.
So anyway, yes.
I was going to point out the seven liquids.
Yeah, יד שחט דם. Yad Shachat Dam.
These are the ones that are מטמא.
Metamei. Yeah, יד שחט דם. Yad Shachat Dam. יין, Yayin, דם, Dam,
look, blood of a מת Meis is טמא. Tamei. שמן, Shemen, חלב.
Chalav. So that would be interesting if it would be milk that
would come out of a מת Meis but that's חלב בהמה. Chalav
behemah. I don't know if that's... I don't think it's by חלב
אישה. Chalav ishah. Yeah,
טל, Tal, dew. דם Dam and מים. Mayim. So anyway, so that's...
you used דם Dam twice. Yeah, you used דם Dam twice.
You did דבש.
Dvash. דבש Dvash is the other one.
Okay anyway, all right.
Why
isn't tears count as מים? Mayim?
That's so that's it.
Not all not
right. So not everything that is chemically water is what... why the
very fact that you needed to include dew, dew is obviously all
water, right? Means that water, you know, for them only meant you
know else you know only basically meant... it wasn't just things with
water component to them. Right exactly. It's not just things with water
component to them. All right, so let's go on. So that was
just wrapping up that nice digression about the blood and blood with
mixed with water etc. and now we discussed blood of a corpse
is like the corpse itself but other liquids not. Now we can
finally move on. חולין פ"ז. Chullin pei zayin. תנן Tenan הניטז ושעל
הסכין. Hanitaz v'she'al hasakin. So blood that splatters that or that's on
the knife, so do you have to do כיסוי Kisuy with it
or not? So the תנא קמא Tanna Kamma says... so רבי יהודה
Rabbi Yehuda said you do not. So the תנא קמא Tanna Kamma
was not clear. So let's take a look.
תנו רבנן. Tannu Rabbanan. וכיסהו, V'chiseihu,
you should cover it. מלמד שדם הניטז ושעל הסכין חייב לכסות. Melamed
she'dam hanitaz v'she'al hasakin chayav l'chasos. You have to cover it. Cover
it means all of it. אמר רבי יהודה, Amar Rabbi Yehuda, אימתי,
Eimasai, when is that true? בזמן שאין שם דם אלא הוא. Bizman
she'ein sham dam ela hu. If that's the only blood you can
find. אבל יש שם דם שלא הוא, Aval yeish sham dam she'lo
hu, if there's other blood, פטור מלכסות, Pattur mi'l'chasos, you are exempt
from covering it. תניא אידך, Tanya idach, we taught in another ברייתא.
Baraisa. וכיסהו, V'chiseihu, you should cover it. מלמד שכל דמו חייב לכסות.
Melamed she'kol damo chayav l'chasos. You have to cover all the blood.
Like the first opinion before. מכאן אמרו. Mikan amru. דם הניטז ושעל
האגפיים. Dam hanitaz v'she'al ha'agafayim. Blood that splattered and here אגפיים Agafayim
not not what we said before, which was... what was the phrase
before? ושעל הסכין. V'she'al hasakin. Here אגפיים Agafayim means on the on
the wings, which רש"י Rashi basically says on the walls of the
slaughterhouse. So there's blood splattered, it's on the walls. חייב לכסות. Chayav
l'chasos. Which will make it pretty difficult. Or you scrape it off
or I don't know you threw you have to I don't know,
cake the dirt on the walls. So anyway, אמר רבן שמעון בן
גמליאל. Amar Rabban Shimon Ben Gamliel. רבן שמעון בן גמליאל Rabban Shimon
Ben Gamliel said, במה דברים אמורים, Bamei devarim amurim, שלא כיסה דם
הנפש. She'lo kissa dam hanefesh. Only if you've not covered the life
blood, which is the blood that emerges immediately after שחיטה. Shechitah. אבל
כיסה דם הנפש, Aval kissa dam hanefesh, if you cover the life
blood, פטור מלכסות, Pattur mi'l'chasos, you don't have to cover the other
blood. So the גמרא Gemara says it's there basically is a three-way
debate here. And the גמרא Gemara will spell it out. במאי קמיפלגי?
B'mai kamifligi? What's their what are they debating? רבנן סברי, Rabbanan savri,
the rabbis say דמו Damo means כל דמו. Kol damo. Its blood
means all of its blood. So whether it's on the knife or
on the walls or on you know wherever it is you gotta
you know you gotta cover all the blood. רבי יהודה סבר Rabbi
Yehuda savar דמו, Damo, אפילו מקצת דמו. Afilu miktzas damo. Its blood
means it didn't say כל דמו. Kol damo. It means any amount
of its blood is sufficient. So you don't have to worry about
the knife and you know and the splatter. רבן שמעון בן גמליאל
סבר Rabban Shimon Ben Gamliel savar דמו המיוחד. Damo hamiyuchad. Its blood
means you know the the most important of its blood, the special
blood, which is which is the life blood.
So that
that splatters on the walls?
It could. Then he would say you'd have to cover it. But
now so this is a three-way debate. So first of all there's
a question... I knew Michael was going to ask how we פסק.
Pasken. I was curious also anyway so I checked. It's actually debated
how we פסק Pasken because normally we say you know you would
go by by the תנא קמא, Tanna Kamma, the majority view. But
there's also a general principle that whenever רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda says
אימתי, Eimasai, when is this true, he's coming to clarify the תנא
קמא. Tanna Kamma. The problem here is is that the גמרא Gemara
says there's a three-way debate, sounds like he's not clarifying. So there's
some confusion exactly how to read that גמרא Gemara to whether we
assume רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda is or is not clarifying. A number
of ראשונים Rishonim assume that he is clarifying and we do rule
like him. תוספות Tosafos primarily... the רמב"ם, Rambam, you know there's תוספות
Tosafos has two two opinions but seems to weigh in that favor.
The רמב"ם Rambam says that. Others say no, here רבי יהודה Rabbi
Yehuda is a dissenting opinion and we rule like the חכמים Chachamim
that you cover all the blood. And that's the ראב"ד's Ra'avad opinion.
The other interesting thing is even when they bring down רבי יהודה,
Rabbi Yehuda, you would think if you really פסק Pasken like רבי
יהודה... Rabbi Yehuda... you would say, okay, cover a little bit of
the blood, מקצת דמו, miktzas damo, but that's never how it's framed.
It's always framed like even within רבי יהודה, Rabbi Yehuda, you should
try to cover all the blood. If there's some blood that you
can't cover, don't worry about it. So whether that is within רבי
יהודה's Rabbi Yehuda position like a דרבנן, derabbanan, דאורייתא de'oraisa just cover
a little, דרבנן derabbanan cover everything you can. Or whether even רבי
יהודה Rabbi Yehuda even at a דאורייתא de'oraisa level is not saying
מקצת miktzas means לכתחילה lechatchila only do some. מקצת Miktzas means it
doesn't have to be all, but still it should be as much
as you can is still
how he might understand it at the biblical level. That's not clear.
That's why, because again if you took his way it's formulated to
its logical conclusion it wouldn't just exclude some splatterings, he would say
just do a token covering and you're done. Mordechai, what do you
want to say?
I was just going to say in practice, yes, in practice when
you're doing the שחיטה, shechita, you're covering where the bulk of the...
it almost sounds like רבן שמעון בן גמליאל Rabban Shimon ben Gamliel
but not, because you're covering the bulk of the blood that was
done when you after the cut when the פירכוס pirkus is going
on and the blood's coming out. That sounds to me like דמו.
damo.
But basically you don't go ahead and have to... right, so that's
true also, just rinse it off in the sink. Exactly. Beyond the
question of is רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda מפרש mefareish or not מפרש,
mefareish, it's pretty impossible to
פסקן posken the חכמים Chachamim here. I mean you could never, I
mean what would you blood splatters and whatever it would be crazy
the amount of effort it would take to cover all the blood.
So you have to basically פסקן posken רבן שמעון בן גמליאל Rabban
Shimon ben Gamliel or רבי יהודה, Rabbi Yehuda, and רבי יהודה's Rabbi
Yehuda even the more lenient because he doesn't if you take it
literally מקצת דמו, miktzas damo, then it's not even then any amount.
And that yes so that is definitely...
cleaning the knife I imagine between
one שחיטה shechita and the next. Yeah but then do you clean
into the sink? Exactly. As opposed to like rubbing it off with
dirt and then covering it. You have to clean it anyway. What?
מפרש? Mefareish? Oh, explain or clarify, clarify. Alright let's look now at
the next משנה. mishnah. במה מכסין ובמה אין מכסין. Bameh mechassin uvameh
ein mechassin. Sort of like במה מדליקין ובמה אין מדליקין. Bameh madlikin
uvameh ein madlikin. There are some משניות mishnayos that are framed like
that. With what can you cover, with what can't you cover? So
actually this is an interesting question תוספות Tosafos asks. Sometimes where it
says במה bameh this and במה bameh that, does it start with
what you can or start with what you can't? Right, במה מדליקין
ובמה אין מדליקין, Bameh madlikin uvameh ein madlikin, what's the next phrase?
אין מדליקין. Ein madlikin. Here's what you can't light with. Here it
starts with here's what you can. Maybe the question is which is
the smaller group? We're going to list the smaller group, but maybe
not, I don't know. Let's take a look. Okay, right because you
can imagine tons of things you can't cover with. Presumably the smaller
group are things that you can cover with. So מכסין, mechassin, here's
what you can cover with, בזבל be-zevel feces, which is actually interesting
because we said before שלא יהא מצוה בזויה עליו shelo yehei mitzvah
bezuyah alav and here you're using excrement. But I assume in a
farming society excrement is not so repulsive. It's a natural thing that
you use every single day. What? It's manure, it's fertilizer.
Just don't use your foot.
Don't use your foot, use a shovel. Okay, בזבל הדק, be-zevel ha-dak,
so it has to be thin. The basic point here is is
that it has to be... well we're going to see two qualities
that the גמרא Gemara is going to explain about what you cover
with. Number one is that it can be if you plant things
in it things will grow. It has to be like dirt in
that way that things will grow. The other thing is that it
has to essentially be like dirt that it has to be,
it's not like a cover, it's not like let's say cover it
with a blanket or cover it with...
what? Granular, thank you. It has to be granular. Okay, is that
what you said? I'm sorry Michael. I'm not ignoring you, I just
didn't hear you, which is something I say to my wife. Okay,
anyway, מכסין. mechassin. It's not that you don't hear, it's that you
don't listen. All right, מכסין בזבל הדק, mechassin be-zevel ha-dak, so with
the thin
manure. ובחול הדק, uv-chol ha-dak, thin sand. בסיד be-sid which is like
plaster, ובחרסית uv-charsis which is also like a חרס, cheres, you know,
pottery. ובלבנה uv-leveinah and now these are going to be qualified that
they've been turned into a more dust-like granular thing. ובלבנה, uv-leveinah, excuse
me, a brick. ובמגופה, uv-magufah, even like the seals that they would
use on
barrels, שכתשן, she-ketashan, that you ground them and you turned them into
something granular. אבל אין מכסין, aval ein mechassin, you do not cover
לא בזבל הגס lo be-zevel ha-gas with thick manure, ולא בחול הגס
ve-lo be-chol ha-gas or thick sand, clumpy sand. ולא
בלבנה ובמגופה שלא כתשן, ve-lo be-leveinah u-ve-magufah shelo ketashan, not these other
things that have not been ground up. ולא יכפה עליו את הכלי,
ve-lo yichpeh alav es ha-kli, and you should not just put a
vessel on top of it. Like a cloth on top of it.
It has to actually be something like dirt that actually is not
something you put and you remove but actually, sort of like, gets
sort of ingrained into the
ground. Okay, את הכלי. es ha-kli. כלל אמר רבן שמעון בן גמליאל,
Klal amar Rabban Shimon ben Gamliel, a general principle said רבן שמעון
בן גמליאל, Rabban Shimon ben Gamliel, דבר שמגדל בו צמחים מכסין בו,
davar she-megadel bo tzmachim mechassin bo, something that plants can grow in
you can cover, ושאינו מגדל בו צמחים אין מכסין בו, ve-she'eino megadel
bo tzmachim ein mechassin bo, not something that things will not grow
in. Now again that seems to be like he's not
disagreeing, he's just clarifying. But it also seems like that's not sufficient,
right? It doesn't seem like he's saying like if you have clumps
of manure or clumps of dirt things won't grow in them. Presumably
they will grow just as well. But it seems like that's two
issues. One is what to cover means, that it has to be
either because it's a definition of what is similar to עפר, afar,
that it's granular, or the concept of covering is a type of
a covering which means more of something with something you know granular.
As רש״י Rashi says, there's a very conceptual difference of covering something
with something clumpy and something granular. Something clumpy or solid like a
כלי kli you put it on and you can remove it. Something
more granular sort of you know gets to be part of the
ground and stays there. So either because of the definition of something
of what it means to be like עפר afar or the definition
of what it means to cover has to be granular and in
addition it's not anything that's granular you can't go ahead and you
know let's say take some I don't know
what do you call it like like a rug and turn it
into you know
and chop it up into little pieces and cover with that. It
has to be also like dirt in that in that things can
grow.
Yes organic
matter. Organic. Right. Exactly to create more life.
That's right.
That's a nice point too.
Because the blood is also a type of a life source of
nutrients. Oh I hadn't thought about it like that. That's interesting. I'd
thought about it more I'd thought about it more... That's very nice
cause I'd thought about it more being like the ground you know
I mean the whole the whole imagery... Right they say things can
grow in it. Right
it's it's a very good point I mean really going back... Right.
I was thinking to cover something you have to get it deeper
into the ground so what you put up has to be more
like the ground itself but what you're saying is something different that
there's also the sense of nurturing the ground and allowing life to
come from it. You know the interesting thing to think about all
of this is the imagery in the תורה Torah about the blood
swallowing up the earth swallowing up the blood right when God speaks
to קין Kayin right and he says you know קול דמי אחיך
צועקים אלי kol d'mei achicha tzo'akim elai you know in the תורה
Torah what?
אשר פצתה את פיה asher ptzata et pi'ah right לקחת את דמי
אחיך מידך likachat et d'mei achicha miyadecha and then when the תורה
Torah speaks about murder right the תורה Torah says right
what's the phrase it uses? well
it says הארץ לא יכופר כי אם בדם שפכה ha'aretz lo yechupar
ki im b'dam shafcha but it says something else about the blood
being covered right doesn't
it say? I should have looked it up there's something about not
covering the blood about the blood
not...
there's certainly הארץ לא יכופר ha'aretz lo yechupar but it's...
I think there's about being covered with the blood I have to
check. Anyway so I think this is interesting because this was blood
that was legitimately spilled and since it was blood that was legitimately
spilled you can cover it up and you have to cover it
up so there's you know when blood is is spilled in a
crime and in murder then the crime is to cover it up
right and you have the the ground is like calling out for
the blood that was spilled but here because it's legitimate so you
know and it's there's I think an interesting parallel going on there
that it's that it's okay to cover and it should be covered
and I like the point. Anyway I was thinking about that about
trying to make it like it's really does get in the ground
it doesn't remain exposed because that's you know that's an affront. It's
an affront to cover you know cover up blood that was illegitimately
spilled but it's an affront to leave blood that was legitimately spilled
exposed in that way. Anyway I was thinking about it more being
related to to being like like the earth but I hear your
point the emphasis of organic and it's not so much earthlike. Some
of these things are not totally earthlike they are organic and the
emphasis of being able to grow is a very nice point.
Yeah like with the blood. Yes. Life source is in the blood
so that's being continued on.
Right I hear and that's giving life to other things. Anyway yeah
although one thing
is that you know if you if you do it...
Oh well first of all first of all by the way don't
we have this ארץ אל תכסי דמם eretz al techasi damam that's
in a right so yeah there's a constant there's definitely this constantly
going metaphor. I just have to remember the exact פסוקים psukim about
blood of murder not not letting the earth cover the blood of
murder as opposed to here the blood of legitimate שחיטה shechita we
are actively...
But even if you you know but I mean the only thing
is like let's say you're doing it in like the factories like
we do today and then you know which are regular floors you
have to take some earth and then put it on top.
Well no you have to lay dirt but remember we opened the
פרק perek you have to start by laying the dirt.
I know I know but it's still not going to grow there
because beneath a floor.
I suppose but actually and with this we have to go on
but Michael makes a good point tying it into this which is
the very fact that you have to ensure that there's earth underneath
right which is added was not in the משנה Mishnah whatever you
know but that was understood in an Amoraic setting and we're understood
that that's part of the biblical מצוה mitzvah you know but that
that also sort of creates you're right something can't grow but it
does create this greater sense of sort of of making it like
it's buried in the ground and connected to the ground and so
on because it has a layer of ground underneath it even though
it is a little artificial. Okay let's take a look at the
גמרא. Gemara. היכי דמי חול הדק heichi dami chol hadak what what
does it mean to be sort of thin sand? So אמר רבה
בר בר חנה אמר רבי יוחנן amar Rabbah bar bar Chana amar
Rabbi Yochanan כל שאין היוצר צריך לכתשו kol she'ein hayotzer tzarich lechatsho
anything that the pottery person... what's the word for pottery person... anyway...
potter...
a potter does not have to does not have to grind it.
You make, you use sand, right, in making whatever, the clay, so
if you don't have to grind the sand in order to to
add to make clay, that's what we're talking about. So right, בידי
היוצר, byadei hayotzer, yeah, but ואיכא דמתני לה אסיפא, ve'ika demasni lah
aseifa,
some say it's clarifying the end. אבל אין מכסים לא בזבל הגס
aval ein mechassin lo bezevel hagas you can't use thick
manure ולא בחול הגס velo vechol hagas or thick sand. היכי דמי
חול הגס? heichi dami chol hagas? What's thick sand? אמר רבה בר
בר חנה אמר רבי יוחנן, Amar Rabbah bar Bar Chana Amar Rabbi
Yochanan, כל שהיוצר צריך לכתשו kol shehayotzer tzarich lekatsho anything that the
potter has to grind before they use it to make the clay.
So the גמרא Gemara says מאי בינייהו? mai beinayhu? What's the difference?
You know, it seems like you're saying the same thing. No, איכא
בינייהו, ika beinayhu, this is great because I always tell you, you
know, based on which one you define, you define like you know
it changes what the other group is. So איכא בינייהו דצריך ולא
צריך. ika beinayhu ditzrich velo tzarich. It's something that sort of requires
grinding but not so much, דמפרך פריך, demifrach parich, you can sort
of crumble it with your hands but it doesn't really require grinding.
So one minute, we're going to talk about sawdust... we're going to
talk about sawdust in a minute. So and I need focus people,
we have 20 minutes left. I need
no side conversations. I need focus. We'll get to sawdust. So anyway,
the point of the גמרא Gemara here is that if you say
anything that needs to be ground, so do you need to grind
something that needs to be crumbled? Well yes. No, the point here
is, is that is it appropriate to say that this grinding gets
done to this? The answer is yes. So if you said if
it needs to be ground it's thick, then this would count as
thick because in some element this does need to be ground. If
you say if it doesn't need to be ground it's thin, then
does this not need to be ground? Is that legitimate to say?
Yes, there's a way you could say it doesn't need to be
ground because you don't need to get a grinder, you just need
to crumble it. So you could sort of put this in both
categories. And since you could put it in both categories, it matters
which is the category you're defining. Okay, now the גמרא Gemara continues.
תנו רבנן Tanu Rabbanan we taught, וכסהו vekhissahu you should cover it,
יכול יכסנו באבנים או יכפה עליו את הכלי yachol yechassenu be'avanim o
yichpeh alav et hakeli
maybe you should cover it with stones or put some vessel on
it, תלמוד לומר בעפר Talmud lomar be'afar with dust. ואין לי אלא
עפר ve'ein li ella afar I only know dust, מנין לרבות זבל
הדק וחול הדק minayin lerabbot zevel hadak vechol hadak how do I
know thin manure and thin sand, ושחיקת אבנים ושחיקת חרסית ushchikat avanim
ushchikat charsiss
so here you have even ground stones, right? Now do things grow
in ground stones? That's a little funny. Anyway, and the grinding of
pottery and ונעורת של פשתן דקה une'oret shel pishtan daka
very thin tuffs of flax, so that's like a type of vegetation.
Flax is not flax grows in the ground, it does not come
from an animal, so it is something that is more or sort
of more from the natural world that way. ונסורת של חרשים דקה
unesoret shel charashim daka and there's your sawdust, thin sawdust, וסיד וחרסית
ולבנה ומגופה שכתשן vesid vecharsiss ulvenah umgufah shekatshan and all these other
things that were ground, תלמוד לומר וכסהו Talmud lomar vekhissahu you shall
cover it. Now some of these things do not seem so organic
or so much that you could grow in, particularly I would say
the... well flax maybe if it comes if it's a type of
a seed, but the rock... and
so anyway
תוספות Tosafot says maybe I don't know תוספות Tosafot well תוספות Tosafot
has a discussion about metal and he says like maybe it adds
to to other dirt if it's something is grown in other dirt.
But I can't see how rock... what were we looking at? Well
we'll get to it in a minute. I can't see how rock
adds anything. What?
Sometimes you see trees growing out of what appears to be rock.
Yeah there's little earth parts in there.
Oh you mean some rocks aren't really rocks.
Well the roots are in the dirt I guess, but
they're growing through it, they're not growing from it, right?
Probably in the seams.
No or like in the crevices some dirt got in there then
it grew.
Sure, I don't know.
Yeah, very
soft.
I don't know. I'm not saying you can't grind it. I'm saying
anyway it's not exactly clear
if everybody agrees to the line in the משנה Mishna things that
things can grow in. It could be that there's also an approach
which is basically things that maybe are organic or maybe are like
from the natural world and are you know and are granular but
it's not necessarily clear that that principle "things grow in" is necessarily
held by everyone. Anyway תלמוד לומר Talmud lomar the verse teaches וכסהו
vekhissahu you shall cover it. So meaning to what however they learn
that out... רש"י Rashi says since it doesn't say בעפר יכסנו be'afar
yechassenu which would have which would have emphasized it must be עפר,
afar, since it starts with the word וכסהו vekhissahu then we don't
treat בעפר be'afar as totally limiting. Now the גמרא's Gemara later going
to ask what about כלל ופרט? klal uprat? But anyway here we're
saying since בעפר be'afar came second we're able to say וכסהו vekhissahu
even with other things as well. יכול שאני מרבה זבל הגס וחול
הגס ושחיקת כלי מתכת ולבנה ומגופה שלא כתשן yachol she'ani marbeh zevel
hagas vechol hagas ushchikat kely mateches ulvenah umgufah shelo katschan maybe I
would include all these other things and one of the things mentioned
besides thick things is is metal, right? Maybe I would... so that
we're going to exclude. וקמח וסובין ומורסן vekemach vesubin umorsan and how
about flour and other types of like you know these other types
of things are like bran and so on. So here are types
of like plant you know plant products. תלמוד לומר בעפר. Talmud lomar
be'afar. Okay what does that tell you? ומה ראית לרבות אלו ולהוציא
את אלו? uma ra'ita lerabbot elu ulhotzi et elu? What's your line
of distinction? So אחר שריבה הכתוב ומיעט achar sheriba hakatuv umiat so
there's a more an inclusive verb וכסהו vekhissahu it seems general and
a limiting word בעפר. be'afar. מרבה אני את אלו שהן מין עפר
marbeh ani et elu shehen min afar I'll include these that are
a type of dust ומוציא אני את אלו... umotzi ani et elu...
מין עפר, min afar, or for the others that are not a
type of dust. So what does it mean type of dust, not
a type of dust, what's the difference? So it means it has
some of the qualities of dust, which number one means granular, but
the other interesting thing is it does exclude metal and it, on
the one hand, metal, no; rock, yes. Aren't they both basically the
same minerals? And on the other hand also it says flax, yes,
but flour, no. Well, those are just, you know, granular stuff from
the, from the plant world. So unless it, it is an assumption
that it is a question about whether things can grow, and the
הגמרא Gemorah was talking about, I don't know what it was talking
about, rocks either assumed, talking about a certain type of a rock,
or assumed that the rock actually can things can grow in ground-up
rocks and they can't grow in the other stuff. Like bran? Have
you ever tried planting a seed in bran? You think it'll grow?
But I've tried planting a seed... I know. I don't know, I
don't really get it. Okay. אימא, Eima,
so now the הגמרא Gemorah says why not say וכסהו vekhissahu
כלל, klal, וכסהו vekhissahu is a general statement, באפר ba'afar פרט, prat,
באפר ba'afar is a limiting, כלל ופרט אין בכלל אלא מה שבפרט,
klal u'prat ein baklal ela mah shebaprat, that you're limited only to
the narrow part. עפר אין מידי אחריני לא, afar in midei achrini
lo, only dust and nothing else. Now, what you could have said
is, this is a great, great place to say that we're doing
ריבוי ומיעוט. ribuy u'miut. Because ריבוי ומיעוט ribuy u'miut gets you one
step ahead of כלל ופרט. klal u'prat. ריבוי ומיעוט ribuy u'miut says
that by the... you have a general and then a limiting, and
with those two combined you have anything like the more narrow term.
You don't need כלל ופרט, klal u'prat, you just need the larger
and the narrower, and then you have that, so maybe you could
say this is of the opinion ריבוי ומיעוט. ribuy u'miut. But since
we know that the הגמרא Gemorah is much more inclined to do
כלל ופרט klal u'prat than ריבוי ומיעוט, ribuy u'miut, and nobody is
debating this law, we have to make it work within the principle
of כלל ופרט. klal u'prat. So within the principle of כלל ופרט,
klal u'prat, why don't we say you're limited to עפר, afar, that
is the limiting term that comes next. So, עפר אין
מידי אחריני לא. afar in midei achrini lo. So אמר רב מרי
משום דהוה כלל הצריך לפרט, Amar Rav Mari mishum dehavah klal hatzarich
liprat, because it is a כלל klal that needs the פרט. prat.
I'll describe what that means in a minute. וכל כלל הצריך לפרט
אין דנין אותו בכלל ופרט. V'khol klal hatzarich liprat ein danin oto
b'klal u'prat. And anytime it needs the פרט, prat, it doesn't follow
the general rule. Now, before I say what this word "needs" means,
I'm going to tell you that this is something for those who
at least do say רבי ישמעאל אומר Rabbi Yishmael Omer in דאווענין,
davening, that you say... for those who say it, that you say
every morning, right? When the י"ג מידות yod gimmel middot is... מכלל
שהוא צריך לפרט ומפרט שהוא צריך לכלל, miklal she'hu tzarich liprat u'miprat
she'hu tzarich liklal, isn't that part of it? One of them? Yeah,
it is, right? What's the exact?
I had a friend who once said that שבועות, Shavuos, you know,
there's no special מצוות mitzvos on שבועות, Shavuos, you know, outside of
the בית המקדש. Beis Hamikdash. I mean, he says no, for him
he says the special מצווה mitzvah is קרבנות Korbanos and say רבי
ישמעאל Rabbi Yishmael because he's up all night, so he's got... anyway,
so it says מכלל שהוא צריך לפרט ומפרט שהוא צריך לכלל. miklal
she'hu tzarich liprat u'miprat she'hu tzarich liklal.
What does that mean? So, oh for god's sake, I got up
and I lost the focus on the camera. Anyway,
so, we gotta get some different camera going on here.
Anyway, so
he said that... so, ah, so what it means is, רש"י Rashi
says what it means is, that צריך tzarich here means that it
teaches, that the... you... that the כלל klal needs to learn something
from the פרט. prat. Even the כלל klal by itself is not
totally clear what it means. What does this mean? So רש"י Rashi
says, because if you just said וכסהו, vekhissahu,
that could refer, it's not just a question about what you use.
The verb itself is ambiguous. וכסהו vekhissahu could mean cover like you
cover something with a blanket or with a vessel, and וכסהו vekhissahu
could mean you cover it like you do with like something granular.
It's a very different type of covering. It's not just about the
object, it's about the verb itself.
Because he just said וכסהו באפר. vekhissahu ba'afar.
I know, but that's the point, that's what it's כלל הצריך לפרט.
klal hatzarich liprat. You can't say it's a כלל, klal, a normal
כלל klal is, you know, like the classic example is, you know,
by money of מעשר שני. Ma'aser Sheni. בכל אשר תאוה נפשך בבקר
ובצאן וביין ובשכר ובכל אשר תשאלך נפשך. Bakhol asher t'aveh nafshekha babakar
u'vatzon u'vayayin u'vashakhar u'v'khol asher tish'al'kha nafshekha. So if you just said,
use it for anything you want, that's pretty self-explanatory. That's a כלל.
klal. That's a classic כלל. klal. If you just said "cover it,"
it's not, it's not a classic כלל klal that it could mean
any object, because there's also a question even what the verb means.
There's different types of covering. So that's what רש"י Rashi says כלל
הצריך לפרט klal hatzarich liprat means, is that it means you don't
even understand what the verb mean, what the כלל klal meant without
the פרט prat clarifying it. תוספות Tosafot says כלל הצריך לפרט klal
hatzarich liprat actually means, let me just take a look what he
says it means...
a minute...
oh, right. תוספות Tosafot says a more simple point, that the word
צריך tzarich means it's just, it's really not so much כלל הוא
צריך לפרט, klal hu tzarich liprat, it's much more that the פרט
prat is needed for a different point. That remember we learned from
באפר ba'afar
that עפר afar has to go below and above. So if it
had just said וכסהו vekhissahu without describing any object, we would not
have known the idea of below and above. So since you know
the תורה Torah needed to use a specific object to communicate the
idea of below and above. which he did בעפר, ba'afar, then you
cannot say בעפר ba'afar is meant as a totally limiting word because
it was needed for a different purpose as well. So it's not
so much a פרט, prat, it's also not so much it's also
not so much the כלל הצריך לפרט, klal hatzarich liprat, it's more
like we are צריך לפרט. tzarich liprat. The פרט prat was needed
to tell you something else as well. Okay, but one of those
two places, since the פרט prat is doing some other duty and
it needed to be there for some other reason, it's not understood
to be totally limiting itself just to the פרט. prat. Okay, alright,
let's continue. I just have to... I know, it's just so annoying.
I gotta get a different camera or something.
Shut off autofocus on the camera.
I keep I forgot to do it because I thought it was
fixed. Okay, let's keep on going. So the גמרא Gemara says like
this: דרש רב נחמן בר רב חסדא Darash Rav Nachman bar Rav
Chisda explains, אין מכסין אלא בדבר שזורעין בו ומצמיח. ein mechasin ela
bedavar shezorin bo umatzmiach.
You don't cover except with something and here is similar like the
like like the משנה Mishnah something that you cover with it and
it and it can grow. You plant in it and it grows.
אמר רבא האי בורכא. Amar Rava Hai burcha. Rava said that's nonsense.
So that's interesting.
בורכא burcha means nonsense.
Yeah, essentially. It's so
so whatever it means. It's an idiomatic expression. That's nonsense, which is
interesting. It seems to have been our משנה, Mishnah, but maybe he
was bothered by the same things we were bothered with and not
all of the distinctions held. Of course, they we didn't know the
other basis of distinguishing either between flour on the one side and
flax on the other, flaxseed on the other. Anyway, אמר ליה רב
נחמן בר יצחק לרבא, amlei Rav Nachman bar Yitzchak le'Rava, so רב
נחמן בר יצחק Rav Nachman bar Yitzchak said to רבא: Rava: מאי
בורכתיה? mai burchasei? Why what's the foolishness? אנא אמריתה ניהליה. Ana amrisani
alei. I told it to him. ומהא מתניתא אמריתה ניהליה U'me'ha matnisa
amrisani alei and I told it to him based on the previous
ברייתא baraita that we taught. That it said there the issue about
it has to be like עפר afar and it has to be
like עפר afar means that it has to be plant and grow.
Now the other question is what's the discussion? Don't didn't they have
it in the משנה? Mishnah? Our משנה Mishnah says: דבר שמגדל בו
צמחים מכסין בו. davar shemegadel bo tzmachim mechasin bo.
So maybe they thought that רבן שמעון בן גמליאל Rabban Shimon ben
Gamliel was disagreeing. And therefore they were resisting it and he's saying:
no, we actually do all this. Okay,
now hold on one second. There might also be a subtle difference
between here it says מגדל צמחים, megadel tzmachim, there it says זורעין
בו ומצמיח.
zorin
bo umatzmiach.
Yes, so תוספות Tosafot actually says that זורעין בו ומצמיח zorin bo
umatzmiach could actually come to exclude other things. Why? If you take
a look at this quickly, this תוספות. Tosafot. אלא בדבר שזורעין בו
ומצמיח למעוטי עפר מדבר, Ela bedavar shezorin bo umatzmiach, le'ma'utei afar midbar,
like a dirt in the desert. כסיד דלא שמי מתניתא דצמחים גדלים
בו מאליהם. Kasid delo shmi matnisa d'tzmakhim gedelim bo me'aleihem.
It's true you do have plants that grow in the desert. אלא
דמה שזורעין בו אינו מצמיח. Ela de'ma shezorin bo einam matzmiach.
If you try to plant a seed in the desert, nothing would
grow. So things can grow in it, but you won't but if
you plant the seed, the seed won't grow. So it's an interesting
difference. So he says that there is a subtle difference between זורעין
ומצמיח zorin umatzmiach as opposed to the משנה Mishnah which is דבר
שמגדל בו צמחים. davar shemegadel bo tzmachim. That there are some types
like he said in the desert cacti grow, but I guess if
you try to plant a cactus seed and water it, I don't
know how cacti grow, but anyway, he says it won't grow through
planting a seed. That's how תוספות Tosafot understands why this is a
little different than the משנה. Mishnah. Okay, let's continue. היה מהלך במדבר.
Haya mehalek bamidbar.
You were going in the desert. ואין לו עפר לכסות. V'ein lo
afar lechasot.
So here you have going in the
desert. Okay, maybe that's you know and that's because you can't use
the dirt of the desert, right? And so מהא מתניתא אמריתה ניהליה.
me'ha matnisa amrisani alei.
From that ברייתא baraita the question is I assume that it meant
the ברייתא baraita above where it said that it has to be
like עפר. afar. But given תוספות's Tosafot explanation that the whole point
is to exclude desert sand, it really makes sense that he's talking
about this coming ברייתא, baraita, right? Because what does it mean you're
going in the desert and you don't have sand to cover? All
you have is sand, right? So what does it mean? So it
means no, sand in the desert if you plant something in the
desert sand, nothing will grow. So how can you have so here
it said: this is why I know that it has to be
something that you can plant in and grow because this describes a
scenario that you don't have anything to cover with in the desert.
If you plant in beach sand it will grow.
I don't know. Okay, maybe that also not.
No but I'm saying חול, chol, what would be the חול chol
then that they're talking about?
Well no, that could just mean like, you know like dirt, not
sand. You mean חול chol granular? Right, right. תוספות Tosafot means sand?
Yeah, it could mean yeah, because yeah I think I think it
means dirt. But it could be like just granular dirt. So it
really becomes a difference, you're right, between dirt and sand. Okay, let's
take a look anyway. So you were going in the desert and
there was nothing to cover with. Okay, so implicitly all that sand
is not good. Where are we?
So what do you do? ואין לו עפר לכסות שוחק דינר זהב
ומכסה. V'ein lo afar lechasot, shochek dinar zahav umechasen. You grind a
gold coin and you so of course you don't have anything but
you do have your chicken which you're going to have for meat
that you brought along. And you have your coins, that makes sense
you have money, and you have your grinder on you. So you
grind your gold coin. Now why can you use we said that
ground metal doesn't work, so we're going to see. היה מהלך בספינה
ואין לו עפר לכסות. Haya mehalek bisafina v'ein lo afar lechasot. That
makes a little more sense. You're going in a boat and you
have nothing to cover. שורף טליתו ומכסה. Soref taliso umechasen. So burn
your טלית, tallis, use ashes. Okay, which also seems like that doesn't
fit like the idea we were saying before, I mean that's not,
you know, מגדל
צמחים. megadel tzmachim. Is that yeah. It's organic material.
It's true.
Okay anyway, so let's see. The גמרא Gemara says like
this: בשלמא שורף טליתו ומכסה אשכחן אפר דאיכא. bishlama soref taliso umechasen,
ashkan eifer d'ika. We know that ashes are called dust, as we'll
see in a minute by אברהם *Avraham*, you know, or not only
אברהם *Avraham*, it says אנוכי עפר ואפר *anochi afar va'eifer*, but other
places it uses those terms interchangeably. אלא *Ela* דינר זהב מנלן *dinar
zahav minalan*, how about gold coins? Normally we exclude metal. So אמר
רב זירא *Amar Rav Zeira* ועפרות זהב לו *veafrot zahav lo* because
it says the dust of gold. Since you speak about gold dust,
so specifically it's about gold. Since the תורה *Torah* uses the phrase
dust by gold, gold dust counts as dust. So even though normally
dust means it has the qualities of dirt, here there are some
things that are labeled dust and even if they don't have the
qualities, they also count. So gold dust is labeled dust and that
also counts. תנו רבנן *Tnu rabanan*, we taught in the ברייתא *Baraita*,
אין מכסין אלא בעפר *ein michasin ela be'afar*, you can only use
dust, דברי בית שמאי *Divrei Beit Shammai*. So he rejects everything we've
been talking about. You can't use anything. It's dirt or nothing else.
ובית הלל אומרים *u'Beit Hillel omrim* מצינו אפר שקרוי עפר *matzinu eifer
shekarui afar*. No, ashes are also called dust. Is it just because
of
the other ones?
What? No, presumably other things that are like dust, he would also
say, but even ashes which maybe is not like dust, maybe ashes
do not have מגדל בו *migdalo bo*. But isn't it true? I
mean I assume ashes... Yeah. So I don't know. So there is
a question why they had to say this. Maybe if you even
used ashes from non-organic material, right? Maybe even that. He's saying ashes
in general, there are things that are labeled dust even if they
don't have the qualities of dirt. So maybe even ashes of non-organic
material you could use.
Doesn't this disagree with our משנה *Mishnah*? Right. Okay.
So because it's gotta be something
that you would make the גזירה שוה *gezera shava*... right.
מצינו אפר
שקרוי עפר *Matzinu eifer shekarui afar*, שנאמר *shene'emar* ולקחו לטמא מעפר שרפת
החטאת *velakchu latamei me'afar sereifat hachatat*. You should take for the dead
person from the dust of the burning
of the red heifer. So it calls it dust even though it
means ashes. ובית שמאי *u'Beit Shammai*? ובית שמאי *u'Beit Shammai* would say
עפר שריפה איקרי *afar sereifa ikrai*. It's called dust of burning. עפר
סתמא לא *afar stama lo*, it's not just called dust period. So
here you have basically two categories. Either the characteristics of dust, granular,
רש"י *Rashi* says granular is the act of covering and can grow
vegetation, although we didn't exactly understand how that fit for everything we
were listing, or it's labeled dust which applies to gold dust and
applies to ashes. One more line and now tomorrow's דף *daf* is
all going to be a nice אגדתא Aggadata *aggadeta* to end the
פרק *perek*. We'll start the אגדתא *aggadeta* now. תנא
*Tana*, oh first one more הלכה *halacha* and then we get to
the אגדתא *aggadeta*. הוסיפו עליה *Hosifu alei* השחור והכחול וניקריס פיסולין *hashachor
vehakichal venakris pisulin*. So שחור *shchor* is basically charcoal or not charcoal
itself but the sort of you
know the charcoal dust. So there you have a more generic type
of ashes. Ground up charcoal. כחול *kachol* was a type of a
salve that they used for the eyes, so I don't know exactly
its qualities.
Was it like eye shadow?
Yeah. I can't but obviously we must be talking in some granular
form. וניקריס פיסולין *Venikris pisulin*, רש"י *Rashi* says is also some type
of a dust that accumulates in a mill where they grind things,
but I don't know if that means from the wheat, probably not
because we excluded flour before, so maybe from the crushing of the
stones, but we already included stone. So I don't really know exactly
what these are.
And flax you said.
And flax we said. And also as we said, even the principles
don't at least in my mind I can't fully understand how they
explain the details. ויש אומרים *Ve'yesh omrim* and some say אף הזרניך
*af hazarnich*, even הזרניך *zarnich* which רש"י *Rashi* says is, I don't
know, a form of, I have no idea. What, arsenic?
Yeah.
Chalk.
Wow.
Arsenic
is a poison.
It's also used for cosmetic powder, oh
and antimony, that's what, צביעה *tzvia*. It's a metallic substance.
Okay. So you have so again I don't know why some metallic
substances are now being included.
What they included was שחיקת כלי *shchikat k'li* from a כלי *k'li*,
so maybe...
it then said שחיקת מתכות *shchikat matachtot*, it said כלי מתכות *k'li
matachtot*, no you're right כלי *k'li*. Anyway I don't know but there's
no reason that should be. All right. אמר רבא *Amar Rava*, now
so we can leave with a question mark of exactly what the
lines of distinction are and now we move on to אגדתא *aggadeta*.
אמר רבא *Amar Rava*: בשכר שאמר אברהם אבינו *bischar she'amar Avraham Avinu*
ואנוכי עפר ואפר *ve'anochi afar va'eifer*, I am like dust and ashes,
right when he was challenging God about סדום ועמורה *Sodom va'Amorah*, זכו
בניו לשתי מצוות *zachu banav lishtei mitzvot*: אפר פרה *eifer parah*, the
ashes of the פרה אדומה Parah Adumah. *parah adumah* which purifies them.
Now you're assuming it was going to say כיסוי הדם *kissuy hadam*
which is what we're talking about, but no. ועפר סוטה Sotah, *ve'afar
sotah*, the עפר *afar* of the סוטה *sotah*. So the גמרא *Gemara*
says: וליחשוב נמי עפר כיסוי הדם *velachashev nami afar kissuy hadam*? How
about our פרק *perek*? Says: התם הכשר מצוה איכא הנא ליכא *hasam
hechshir mitzvah ika hana leka*. There you're doing a מצוה *mitzvah* but
you don't get any benefit out of it because even without doing
it you can eat the meat. Whereas here it might be that
it's less of a מצוה *mitzvah*. It's not like you get brownie
points. It's actually quite ironic, right? You sort of get מצוה *mitzvah*
points for doing כיסוי הדם *kissuy hadam*. You don't get מצוה *mitzvah*
points for doing the סוטה *sotah* process. But nevertheless you get a
benefit from it because it resolves right because it you know it
עושה שלום בין איש לאשתו *oseh shalom bein ish l'ishto* and they're
able to put aside the suspicions and go on. So therefore it's
something that's a real reward in the sense of some real concrete
benefit. I was actually thinking we'll end with this. I was trying
to think about... the way it connects particularly to אברהם. So the,
the פרשה סוטה parsha Sotah thing I figured out, I mean, not
exactly סוטה, but you know, the whole thing there about for I
mean, there you do have those things. First of all, the tension
between him and שרה Sarah and, and the jealousy with הגר Hagar
and you know, who's the real wife and so on. And then
it comes up again in חז"ל Chazal because חז"ל Chazal say the
whole thing about when שרה Sarah has had יצחק Yitzchak that everybody
was saying, oh sure, after she was with אבימלך, Avimelech, then she
has יצחק, Yitzchak, you know, so that there was all these like
suspicions. So there's an interesting thing, you know, that that sort of
I can see some connections there. I didn't get the פרה אדומה.
Somebody maybe can can figure that out and tell me next time.
Okay, so to be continued tomorrow where we'll end with some אגדתא
and